Guide to the Pelham Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Pelham papers
1742-1749
OSB MSS 48
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.25
(1 box)
Correspondence mainly concerning the War of Austrian Succession. There is a significant amount of correspondence from Robert Hampden and from Thomas Hunter regarding various aspects of the war.
Pelham, Henry, 1695?-1754
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Please consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
HENRY PELHAM (1695?-1754)
Henry Pelham was elected to the House of Commons to represent Seaford in 1717. In 1720, he was appointed treasurer, and in 1721, one of the lords of the treasury. In 1722, he returned to the House of Commons to represent Sussex, a position that he held for the rest of his life. In 1724, he resigned from the treasury and was appointed secretary of war. In 1725, he was appointed a member of the privy council, and in 1730, paymaster of the forces. In 1743, he was appointed lord of the treasury and chancellor of the exchequer.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence mainly concerning the War of Austrian Succession. There is a significant amount of correspondence from Robert Hampden and from Thomas Hunter regarding various aspects of the war.
Austrian Succession, War of, 1740-1748; Hampden, Robert Hampden, Viscount, 1706-1783; Hunter, Thomas Orby, approximately 1716-1769; Pelham, Henry, 1695?-1754
- Correspondence, 1746 Jul 20, Jul 24
  - Batthyany, Comte de. 2 ALS (copies) to Thomas Hunter, [n.p.], 1746 Jul 20, Jul 24 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    In French, requesting £100 sterling from the English Treasury.
  - Clayton, Jasper. ALS to Henry Pelham, Ghent, 1743 Jan 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Tells of his sorrow because his report on food supply has been contradicted, but claims that Lord Stair will support him in his views.
  - Drummond, Robert Hay, Abp. of York, 1711-76. Letter (copy) to [?], Hanaw, 1743 Jun 28 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Hampden, Robert Hampden Trevor, 1st Viscount, 1706-1783. 11 ALS to Henry Pelham, The Hague, 1744 May 12-1745 Sep 21 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    "Most Secret" letters concerning the whole range of activity associated with the war. Includes thoughts on the lamentable state of English military operations, much European royalty, commanders of armies, politics, finances, conventions, treaties.
  - Harrington, William Stanhope, 2nd earl of, 1719-1779. Receipt, signed, 1749 Jun 27 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    For ammunition from Montagu.
  - Honeywood, Sir Phillip, d. 1752. ALS to [Henry Pelham], Ghent, 1743 Feb 12 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Thanks Pelham for his kind words to the King regarding Honeywood's desire for "wearing a Ribband." Wonders when his promotion to General shall come. Claims that spirits have risen since the arrival of 20,000 Dutch troops.
  - Hume, Abraham. Diary (extract), Bruxelles, 1742 Aug 22-Oct 29 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Contemporary manuscript copy. Concerning the managing of food stores and forage for the Hanoverian and Hessian troops.
  - Hunter, Thomas Orby, ca. 1716-1769
    Concerning the day to day expenses and progresses of the War of the Austrian Succession. Remarks on the Jacobite rebellion.
    - 3 ALS to Henry Pelham, Aix la Chappelle, Frankfort, 1743 Jul 26-Sep 17 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 6 ALS to Henry Pelham, Antwerp, 1745 Jun 9-Nov 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 11 ALS to Henry Pelham, Rotterdam, 1746 Apr 15-Jul 29 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 7 ALS to Henry Pelham, Rotterdam, 1746 Aug 16-Nov 22 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 10 ALS to Henry Pelham, Rotterdam, 1747 Feb 28-Jun 20 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 10 ALS to Henry Pelham, Rotterdam, 1747 Jul 7-Oct 31 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 2 ALS to Henry Pelham, The Hague, 1748 Oct 18/29-Oct 21/Nov 1 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Montagu, John Montagu, 2nd duke of, 1688?-1749. ALS to [Henry Pelham], Blackheath, 1742 Nov 2 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    "The book of the Establishment of the French army is not to be bought here, and it is forbid to be printed in France." He copied the number of French Land Forces from one of these books and sends it along (not included).
  - Mordaunt, Sir John, 1697-1780. 3 ALS to [Henry Pelham], Bamberg, Egra, Pilsen, 1748 Aug 11, Aug 29, Sep 2 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Tells of dissatisfaction with the Russians as allies, especially on the march into Bohemia. Very cynical about the "virtuous set of Patriots" who shall bring on a new war.
  - Nicoll, John Luke. 2 ALS to [Henry Pelham?], Rotterdam, 1748 Aug 13, Sep 13 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Concerning finances of the late campaigns of the War of Austrian Succession. Mentioning the "Spirit of Riot and Confusion" in Holland, he scoffs at this in the first letter; later he learns that the Prince of Orange has been detained by magistrates in Amsterdam.
  - Pelham, Henry, 1695?-1754. AL (draft) to Thomas Hunter, London, 1747 May 8 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Requests the continuance of correspondence from Hunter. Informs him that Maj. General Huske is to take command of a certain group of troops in Holland. He is to receive credit from Hunter, as deputy paymaster.
  - Walpole of Wolverton, Horatio Walpole, 1st Baron, 1678-1757
    - ALS to [?], Cockpitt, 1745 Jan 4 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - ALS to [Charles Townshend], Chateau, 1729 Sep 5 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - ALS to Sir Robert Walpole, The Hague, 1734 Nov 9 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Documents, 1742-43, n.d.
  - Computations regarding the War of the Austrian Succession., 1742-43, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Convention for the Campaign, 1745 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - "Copy of Mr. Gore's Letter to Mr. Corn. Munter of Hry. Bicker Jans, 24th June 1743.", 1743 Jun 24 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - "Translation of a printed paper dispers'd underhand at the Hague the the 18th August 1747.", 1747 Aug 18 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Warrants Countersigned at the Treasury out of Contingencies in Flanders, and included in Mr. Hunter's Memorial., [1742] (Box 1, Folder 26)